welcome to lecture nine about virtual memory
here you have the reading instructions is chapter
3.3 to 3.6 and as always you have the pointers
to other parts of the facultative book you can
have a look at if you want to
complement a bit the discussion
so the objective here is to continue our
discussion about memory management going back
from where we left so paging and describe
the benefits of virtual memory we will discuss
concepts like demand paging page-replacement
algorithms and allocations of page frames
and then we will discuss what the working
set model is thrashin and so on these are a
bit more advanced concepts but hopefully
it will be clear let's start with a
rapid recap and the introduction so the last
thing we discussed last time was paging we said
we take a process we divide the logical space
into pages then we take the physical memory
and that is divided into frames the size of a
frame and a page is the same we even maintain
stuff on disk organized into pages so that
when we load a process we put pages into
frames and this is what I said the page size is
equal to the frame size and of course we need
a page table so that we can translate the logical
addresses to actual physical addresses and as you
can hopefully see now since we have this
disjoint way of maintaining the logical addresses
and or the logical space and the physical space
with this intermediate thing that is the pages /
frames and how we translate addresses using the
page table we have less fragmentation paging
doesn't have external fragmentation it has only
internal one and that you can control better with
the page size plus again as long as you have
enough free frames you can load a process
independently of where the frames are which is
not true for example with contiguous allocation
we have better protection this is since even
the segmentation before paging we discussed
and it's also faster to load and swap processes
this we will discuss now because now as you
can imagine it's enough to swap some pages
rather than all the pages but let's see this
one step at a time so the first question here
we should think about is what would happen if
the operating system was sort of lying let's
say and not really loading all the pages into
the frames when you want to start a process so i'm
saying that it just does not load a specific page
here not that it places it in a different
frame well of course the intuitive answer here
would be well of course it would be a problem
because when I access the page and I don't find
it in a frame then that of course it's a
problem which is of course a correct observation
but then you could think but when would that be
a problem? because it is a problem only if you
try to access page three as long as you don't
access page 3 whether it is or not in the real
physical memory doesn't really play any
difference for the process that is
run by the operating system so if you want to
oversimplify what virtual memory is it's basically
something like this it's to use paging but not
to put everything really into the physical memory
when you start the process but rather put it
there only when it looks like it's really needed
so basically waiting until the process says
I want a specific page and then place the
page in memory if it's not already there
a motivation behind this could be that
of course a process is quite large it
contains a lot of routines and so on
and it's not that you are really running all
these things at the same time all the time
this we mentioned it a bit before maybe in some
discussion if I remember correctly and we will
mention it now again there is this concept of
locality so you start running a function so for a
certain period of time you will be running that
function it will run the instructions that are
close by in memory because they belong to the same
function you will use the same variables many
times in the same portion of memory and so on so
for a certain amount of time you will stay there
then you change function you go to another place
in memory where you are running other things it's
not that you use all the code all the time so
there might even be parts of the code that are
not actually used during an execution you can
have unusual routines you can have error codes
maybe there is no error you don't
need to run so you can see that
there is a reason why I don't really want to
load everything because it's not that you really
need everything all the time if you can load
stuff only when it's needed it can be of course
an advantage so first of all you can run more
processes than the ones you could run if you load
all of them at the same time so you
are not really constrained any longer
by the physical memory you have each
program takes less memory while running
so you can run more programs at the same time
it also takes less time to load the program
because you don't have to load all the pages
you just load some of them so when you say start
a process the responsiveness gets better because
instead of loading I don't know five gigabytes
of stuff maybe you can run initially with
a bunch of hundred megabytes and be more
responsive now of course as
always trade-offs what are the trade-offs in
this case if you use this mechanism which places
a page into a frame only when it's really needed
well of course that you need a mechanism to
check if the page is there or not so the
operating system needs a way to detect that the
process is trying to access something that is not
in memory and react rapidly and here you will
see it's again collaboration with the hardware
there will be a degradation in the performance
accessing something that is in memory
compared to trying to access something that is
in memory finding out is not there waking up the
operating system letting the operating system
react and go to the disk fetch the page place
it where it should be update the page table and
tell the process okay now you can access of course
takes a lot of time you will pay this penalty so
the idea is that you should not pay this penalty
too much otherwise maybe it's not worth
the benefits you have with virtual memory
and there will be more but
let's look at them later on